Guide to the Charles Allan Madison Papers TAM 133
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Charles Allen Madison Papers
1918-1935
TAM 133
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
7.25 Linear feet (12 boxes)
Charles Allan Madison was a publishing executive and author of several books on labor, liberal and progressive leaders, publishing history and Jewish topics. He was born in Kiev and emigrated to the United States in 1906. He earned an MA in comparative literature from Harvard University in 1922 after which he moved to New York City to begin his long career as an editor. He first worked with the American Book Company from 1922-1924, and then went to Henry Holt and Company where he remained for the next 38 years. The collection includes Madison's manuscripts and correspondence with a number of prominent individuals, including: Howard Fast, Harold L. Ickes, Robert M. LaFollette Jr., Eleanor Roosevelt, Norman Thomas, Oswald Garrison Villard, among others.
Madison, Charles Allan
Provenance
Gift of Mrs. Jeppy Yarensky (daughter), 1987.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Charles Allan Madison (1895-1985), was a publishing executive and author of several books on labor, liberal and progressive leaders, and on publishing history and Jewish topics. He was born April 16, l895, in Kiev, Russia, the son of David (a tailor) and Bessie (Burakovsky) Madison. He emigrated to the United States with his family in 1906 and settled in Detroit Michigan where they joined his sister who had arrived a year previous with her husband and his parents. Madison was educated in the Detroit public schools. He attended the University of Michigan by working his way through and received his BA degree in 1921. A year of graduate study at Harvard University earned him an MA in comparative literature in 1922. He then moved to New York City to begin his long career as an editor, first with American Book Company 1922-1924, and then with Henry Holt and Company. He remained with Holt for 38 years and retired in 1962. He married Edith Hellman, an artist on July 1, l924, and they had one child, a daughter Jepitha "Jeppy" (Mrs Leonard Yarensky).
Madison began writing verse at the age of eighteen and continued to write and publish even while working as an editor. He contributed many literary and historical essays, and book reviews to various publications on a regular basis: Poet Lore; American Scholar; The Nation; Saturday Review; Yale Review; Chicago Jewish Forum and others. In 1934 he was invited to attend Yaddo a colony for writers and artists in Saratoga Springs, New York. It was possibly here he met and developed a lasting friendship with the authors James T. Farrell and Evelyn Scott.
His early interest was in Yiddish literature and he published several articles on the subject. But by the 1940's his interests turned to the liberal movement in America. His first book, Critics and Crusaders: A Century of American Protest(Henry Holt, 1947) received favorable notices. Portions or chapters of the book had actually been first published as historical articles in various journals. The format of the book was basically a series of 21 selected short biographies of abolitionists, utopians, anarchists, dissident economists, militant liberals, socialists and "intransigent New Dealers." This book was followed by two more works on similar subjects: American Labor Leaders(Harper, 1950), and Leaders and Liberals in 20th Century America(Ungar, 1961).
After his retirement in 1962 as editor at Holt Publishing, Madison wrote four books about the history of publishing and/or on Jewish topics. They were: Yiddish Literature(Ungar, 1968), Eminent American Jews(Ungar, 1971), Irving to Irving: Author-Publisher Relations(Bowker, 1974), and Jewish publishing in America: the impact of Jewish writing on American culture(Sanhedrin, 1976). He also wrote two autobiographical manuscripts. Madison died February 2nd, 1985 two months short of his 90th birthday.
Chronology:
1921: First article published in Poet Lore.
1922-24: First job: assistant editor with American Book Co.; published several articles on Judaic subjects in Poet Lore, The Nation, etc.
1924: Marries Edith Hellman, artist. Becomes editor at Henry Holt Publishing. Important advancement.
1933: Invited to attend Yaddo in summer. Meets James T. Farrell and Evelyn Scott (Metcalf).
1940-46: Published several articles which are later to be chapters in his first book.
1947: First book published: Critics and Crusaders: a Century of American Protest Holt.
1949: Several articles published on labor leaders
1950: Book published: American Labor Leaders Harpers.
1954-57: Articles in The Nation: American liberal, radicals.
1959: 2nd edition: Critics and Crusaders. Ungar.
1961: Book: Leaders ans Liberals in 20th Century America, Ungar.
1962: Retires as editor of College and Textbook Divison at Holt Publishing. Book: 2nd edition: American Labor Leaders.
1963: Articles on book publishing.
1966: Books: Book Publishing in America McGraw ;The Owl Among the Colophons Holt
1968: Book: Yiddish Literaure: Its Scope and Major Writers, Ungar
1970: Book: Eminent American Jews. Ungar.
1974: Book: Irving to Irving: Author-Publisher Relations, Bowker.
1976: Last book published: Jewish Publishing in America: The Impact of Jewish Writing on American Culture, Sanhedrin.
Scope and Content Note
Series I. Correspondence, is organized into six subseries: A. Chronological, B. Individuals, C. Unions (David Dubinsky, Carl Haessler, Fred Thompson), D. Yaddo (James T. Farrell and Evelyn Scott), E. Manuscripts, F. Personal. The bulk of the correspondence concerns his writings, and includes a number of prominent individuals to whom he sent manuscripts for comment, including Charles Beard, Henry Black, Hugo Black, Solon DeLeon, John Dewey, Howard Fast, Harold L. Ickes, Agnes Inglis, Robert M. LaFollette Jr., Eleanor Roosevelt, Norman Thomas, Lewis Untermeyer, Oswald Garrison Villard, and Henry A. Wallace.
Series II. Writings, is organized into three subseries: A. Miscellaneous Manuscripts, B. Published Manuscripts, C. Unpublished Manuscripts. It contains manuscripts for six of Madison's books, many article-length manuscripts (for both unpublished and published writings), including a file of short stories, and several book-length unpublished manuscripts, two autobiographical (The Inner Quest and The Past Is Prologue), a biographical study (The Agony and Achievement of Ludwig Lewisohn), and two historical novels: Call Back Yesterday (an American radical bildungsroman), and The Day Breaketh (Jewish life in Eastern Europe).
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence; II. Writings.
Folders are generally arranged chronologically within each series.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed]
Black, Hugo LaFayette, 1886-1971.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Dubinsky, David, 1892-1982.; Farrell, James T. (James Thomas), 1904-1979.; Fast, Howard, 1914-2003.; Goldman, Mendl, b. 1902; Haessler, Carl, 1888-1972.; Henry Holt and Company.; Ickes, Harold L. (Harold LeClair), 1874-1952.; La Follette, Robert M. (Robert Marion), 1895-1953.; Lewisohn, Ludwig, 1882-1955.; Lowenthal, Marvin, 1890-1969.; Madison, Charles Allan.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Scott, Evelyn, 1893-; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968.; Thompson, Fred, 1900-1987.; Untermeyer, Louis, 1895-1977.; Villard, Oswald Garrison, 1872-1949.; Wallace, Henry A. (Henry Agard), 1888-1965.; Yaddo (Artist's colony).; American literature--20th century.; American literature--Jewish authors.; Articles.; Authors--Political and social views.; Autobiography (genre); Book editors.; Correspondence.; Jewish publishers.; Labor unions--United States.; Literature publishing.; Manuscripts for publication.; Politics and literature.; Yiddish literature.
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Subseries A: Chronological Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1918-1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1930-1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1943 Jan-June (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1943 Jul-Dec (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1947 Jan (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1947 Feb (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1947 Mar-June (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, 1947 Jul-Dec (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence, 1962 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence, 1962 Apr-May (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence, 1962 June (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence, 1962 Jul-Dec (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence, 1963 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence, 1963 Mar-Apr (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence, 1963 May-Sept (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Correspondence, 1963 Oct-Dec (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence, 1964 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence, 1964 Mar (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence, 1964 Apr-June (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence, 1964 Jul-Oct (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Correspondence, 1964 Nov (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Correspondence, 1964 Dec (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Correspondence, 1965 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Correspondence, 1965 Mar-Apr (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Correspondence, 1965 May-Jul (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Correspondence, 1965 Aug (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Correspondence, 1965 Sept-Dec (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Correspondence, 1966 Jan-Sept (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Correspondence, 1966 Oct-Nov (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Correspondence, 1966 Dec (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Correspondence, 1980 Jan-June (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Correspondence, 1980 Jul-Dec (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Suberies B. Correspondence: Individuals
    - Charles Beard 1944-1947 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Justice Hugo Black 1952,1966,1968-70, 1952, 1966-1970 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Solon DeLeon 1946, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - John Dewey 1932, 1944, 1949, 1932-1949 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Howard Fast 1945,1947 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Harold L.Ickes 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Agnes Inglis 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Robert M. LaFollette Jr. 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Eleanor Roosevelt 1961 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Norman Thomas 1961 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Oswald Garrison Villard 1940, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Lewis Untermeyer 1948 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Henry A. Wallace 1947-1943, 1958-1959, 1961-1964, 1937-1943, 1958-1964 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Suberies C. Correspondence: Unions
    - Amalgamated Clothing Workers - Charles W. Erving, 1949; Jacob S. Potofsky, 1950, 1949, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen - Alexander F. Whitney, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Congress of Industrial Organizations CIO - Stanley H. Ruttenberg, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Industrial Worker (IWW) - Fred Thompson 1947 (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - International Garment Workers (ILGWU) - David Dubinsky 1948 (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - International Longshoremen & Warehousemen (ILWU) - Lincoln Fairley 1949, 1961-1962; Morris Watson, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - United Auto Workers Union - Frank Winn 1961 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Federated Press (Union Press Service) - Carl Haessler 1949 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Suberies D. Correspondence: Yaddo
    - Yaddo, 1933-1935 (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - James T. Farrell, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - James T. Farrell, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - James T. Farrell, 1935-1937 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - James T. Farrell, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Evelyn Scott, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Evelyn Scott, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Evelyn Scott, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - Evelyn Scott, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Evelyn Scott, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Evelyn Scott, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - Evelyn Scott, 1947-1949 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Suberies E. Correspondence: Manuscripts
    - Corresponcence: Manuscripts, 1951-1958 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Corresponcence: Manuscripts, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - Corresponcence: Manuscripts, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Corresponcence: Manuscripts, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - Corresponcence: Manuscripts, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - Corresponcence: Manuscripts, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - Corresponcence: Manuscripts, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - Corresponcence: Manuscripts, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - Corresponcence: Manuscripts, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - Corresponcence: Manuscripts, 1974-1984 (Box 4, Folder 108)
  - Suberies F. Correspondence: Personal
    - Correspondence: Personal, 1962-1965 (Box 5, Folder 110)
    - Correspondence: Personal, 1966-1969 (Box 5, Folder 111)
    - Correspondence: Personal, 1970-1977 (Box 5, Folder 112)
- Series II: Writings
  - Subseries A. Miscellaneous Manuscripts
    - American Publishers, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - American Labor Leaders, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Artistic Elements of Fictional Characters, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Autobiography, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Baldwin, Roger, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Black, Hugo L., undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Book Clubs, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Book Publishing in America, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Brandeis, Louis D., undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Brooks, Van Wyck, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Childe Roland to the Tower Came, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Dewey, John, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Dynamic Democracy, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Goldman, Mendel, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Hazlitt, William, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Holt, Henry, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Industrial Workers of the World, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Jewish Books, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Jewish Contributions to American Civilization, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Jewish Publishing in America, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - LaFollette, Robert M., undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Lewisohn, Ludwig, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Lowenthal, Marvin, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Meredith, George, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Moses and Lincoln, undated (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - New York Vignettes, undated (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Norris, George W., undated (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Organized Labor, undated (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Pater, Walter, undated (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Published Reviews, undated (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Roosevelt, Theodore, undated (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Russian Revolution, Beginnings of, undated (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Shadows Over Democracy, undated (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Short Stories (unpublished), undated (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - The Social Crusader in America, undated (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - Speeches on Israel, undated (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Strawberries, undated (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Thesis for Creative Listening, undated (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Wallace, Henry A., undated (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Wilson, Woodrow, undated (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Yiddish in Israel, undated (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - Yiddish Literature, undated (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - Yiddish Theatre, undated (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - Yiddish Writers, undated (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Subseries B. Published Manuscripts
    - 1947 Critics and Crusaders (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1950 American Labor Leaders (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - 1968 Yiddish Literature (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - 1970 Eminent American Jews (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 1974 Irving to Irving (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - 1976 Jewish Publishing in America (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Subseries C. Unpublished Manuscripts
    - The Agony and Achievement of Ludwig Lewisohn, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Call Back Yesterday, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - The Day Breaketh, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - The Inner Quest, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - The Past is Prologue - Version 1, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - The Past is Prologue - Version 2, undated (Box 9, Folder 12)